The title says it all. That's what we'll
be discussing. It's been pretty well
established that drinking coffee has a
host of health benefits. I'll have a
nice little twist for you at the end of
this video on that statement. But by and
large, it's true. Coffee is recognized
as not only safe, but beneficial for our
health. In a brand spanking new
analysis, researchers confirm that
reality. But they take things a step
further by attempting to address if
timing coffee consumption provides more
or less benefit. In this analysis,
researchers performed a prospective
associative study, which means that they
collected data over time from people who
do not consume coffee, the heathens, and
those that do consume coffee but at
different times. The follow-up lasted
for almost 10 years, and the researchers
verified the results with another
database. This is called external
validation and can be quite useful since
you're confirming the results across two
different samples. If there's
consistency, that's excellent news as it
indicates generalizability and
robustness of the primary results.
Anyway, here's the breakdown of the
40,000 participants. The gray is the
non- coffee drinkers, the blue is the
morning drinkers, and the red is the all
day. The comparison of the two coffee
consuming groups across the day is
below. There's a big spike for the blue
morning drinkers and then almost nothing
later, but a consistent amount for the
all day type even into the evening. Now,
if we quantify the amounts of coffee
consumed, we see the increased
consumption in descending order is on
the left side. We're looking at
cardiovascular related deaths and we're
comparing against the black dot up top.
That's the standardized risk. So, people
who don't consume coffee like us
addicts, if the dots and the lines move
to the left of the red line, the
standard risk, there's reduced risk of
cardiovascular mortality. I won't bother
you with the numbers on the right side
because they're included in the lines
and dots that we're focusing on. So,
what do we see here? Well, clearly all
coffee consumption, even over three cups
in the morning, is associated with
reduced risk. Interestingly, all day
consumers do not experience this benefit
because the lines those are called
confidence intervals cross the middle
line indicating we weren't confident
enough in the results to identify an
effect statistically speaking at least.
Now, I realize someone has probably
already commented that sleep is a major
factor in health and people who drink
coffee later in the day likely sleep
worse than those that consume only in
the morning. Don't worry, the
researchers thought of that along with a
lot of other things. We'll get into that
shortly. By the way, here's the all-
cause mortality data. That's including
the cardiovascular mortality that we
just went over, but also indices of like
cancer, uh, kidney disease, and so many
other killers. At least at greater than
one cup of coffee and onward, morning
drinkers again experience benefit, but
again, no effect for all day drinkers.
By the way, a coffee cup is defined as 8
ounces of black coffee. None of this uh
frappe macchiato
uh ultra latte foam six pump uh soy
vanilla coffee. I'm actually not sure if
any of those fit together, but you get
my point. The researchers also did a
dose response curve. The blue is the
morning group and the pinkish is the all
day drinkers. That 1.0 line is the
standard risk. So simply stated, if the
colors cross the 1.0 line, there's no
reduced risk. If they go down, there's
reduced risk in this case of
cardiovascular mortality. Again, on the
horizontal axis, there's the ever
intuitive grams of coffee intake.
Clearly, as coffee intake increases in
the morning, there's a greater and
greater reduced risk. That indicates
that the more coffee you consume, the
better. However, I should caution that
that isn't an invitation to give
yourself heart palpitations trying to uh
meet some more is better goal. In fact,
there's some sobering news on that front
that we'll get into. But before we do
that, I'm going to be covering the age
effect uh caffeine versus caffeine-free
coffee and some other uh continuations
of this analysis in the full version of
this video that you're watching. That
full version along with all my work is
part of the Physionic Insiders which is
linked in the description if you're
interested. That obligatory
advertisement out of the way, there's
more to say on this analysis because I'm
sure there are some obvious questions
that need to be addressed. So, several
nuances here that we need to keep in
mind. These are very important. One, the
effect is generally modest to moderate.
So, ranging from 15 to 30% reduced
relative risk depending on the outcome
and the statistics. So, I probably
wouldn't uh clutch your coffee expecting
it to clear out all the plaque in your
arteries or anything. Although, I'd be
happy to create a video scamming you
into thinking that like I see all too
often on social media if that's what you
really want. It only works with my
special autophagy super coffee. So, be
sure to only buy from
me. Two, I didn't show you the uh
baseline values across uh three groups,
but the non- coffee drinkers were in
several respects quite different from
the coffee drinkers. They were younger,
had lower blood cholesterol, fewer, had
diabetes as a few examples. So, could
the effect be a bit bigger if we
compared against people who are equal in
age and health status? I mean possibly
but likely only slightly because the
researchers did adjust for a number of
factors that I'm sure that you've
thought of already like sleep. Now in
associative studies researchers have to
control or adjust for something called
confounders. These are factors that may
also track with the effect i.e. reduced
cardiovascular mortality for example and
may be the true variable causing the
benefit not the coffee. An obvious one
for those who consume coffee into the
evening is sleep disturbance because
sleep is vital to our health.
Fortunately, the researchers uh rubbed
two brain cells together and adjusted
for far more than just sleep. Here's the
list. They counted for age, sex,
ethnicity, family income, education
level, weight, diabetes, high blood
pressure, high cholesterol, uh smoking,
uh physical activity, diet, uh calorie
intake, tea intake, caffeinated soda
intake, abnormally short sleep, so like
less than 7 hours, and trouble falling
asleep. So after accounting for all
that, we get the results that we just
went over. In the end, is it possible
that there's residual confounding as in
some of these may still provide a small
amount of influence on the analysis or
that the researchers missed a
confounding variable that applies to
thousands of people? Yes. However, the
researchers did a ton of statistics to
address those issues from multiple
angles. Admittedly, I would still like
to see an analysis with many of those
factors equal at baseline instead of
focusing on adjustments, but none of
this indicates a negative result for
coffee, no matter how you slice it. Now,
one more question to answer before we
put this all together into some
applicable takeaways. Why would
consuming coffee throughout the day lose
us all these mortality protection
benefits, especially when controlling
for sleep and sleep disturbances? Well,
the researchers offer two interlin
explanations. One makes more sense than
the other, but you let me know your
thoughts. One, our physiology works on a
circadium rhythm, and that rhythm is
dictated by many molecules secreted by
your cells. Other studies, according to
the researchers, have shown that later
coffee consumption reduces melatonin,
which is a key player in these circadian
rhythms, just as one example. So
interrupting that rhythm or somehow
changing it for the worse could have
seemingly imperceptible health effects.
I think that's a reasonable explanation.
Although we certainly don't know if it
this is like the main mechanism to
explain all this link. On the other
hand, they mentioned that many cells
release pro-inflammatory molecules in
the morning upon waking and the added
coffee consumption in the morning could
reduce their prevalence unlike later in
the day when we need it less because the
pro-inflammatory molecules are much
lower in concentration. Now, I'm not
sold on this one, but it's not exactly a
bad explanation. So, let me know if
either or both or neither makes sense to
you. Okay, so where does that leave us?
What are the takeaways? The takeaway is
that coffee is yet again shown to be a
benefit to our life by reducing
cardiovascular and total mortality risk.
In addition, more within your personal
tolerability indicates greater benefit.
However, coffee consumption should be
finished before noon because later
consumption does not associate with
benefit. At least in this study, you
know, there are even doctors that claim
coffee is killing us and they reference
a molecule in coffee that's poisonous. I
cover it all with many jokes in this
next video. I'll speak with you over
there.
[Music]